A Guide to the Papers of Nathaniel Howell, 1930-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Nathaniel Howell 1930-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12815-d
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The restricted series (Box 11) contains personally identifiable information that prevents its being served to the public.
Acquisition Information
This addition was given to the University of Virginia Library by W. Nathaniel Howell, Director of the Arabian Peninsula and Gulf Studies Program, University of Virginia, on 2006 July 10, 2006.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of U.S. Ambassador W. Nathaniel Howell, former U. S. Ambassador to Kuwait, and current Director of the Arabian Peninsula and Gulf Studies Program, University of Virginia, ca. 1930-2006, ca. 2,250 items (11 boxes, ca. 4.5 linear feet) and chiefly contain activities and correspondence files; papers and photographs concerning the conference The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?; typescripts of his dissertation; lecture tour material; photographs; papers preserved by his mother, Josephine Edwards Howell; and personal memorabilia.
His foreign service papers include address and appointment books; photographs from diplomatic receptions in Kuwait; photographs of US Central Command visits to Pakistan; memorabilia; and photographs of activities at the U.S. embassy during the Iraqi occupation, 1990-1991.
Arrangement
These papers are arranged in four series: Series I: Activities/ Correspondence and Topical Files (Boxes 1-8); Series II: Memoranda Books (Box 8); Series III: Photographs and Photograph Albums (Boxes 9-10); and Series IV: Restricted Material (Box 11), and alphabetically within series.
Contents List
- Series I: Activities/ Correspondence and Topical Files
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1957, 1963 November-1969 May (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1970 January-1979 May (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1980 January-1986 December (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 1987 January-December (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1988 January-May (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1988 June-December (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 1989 January-December (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1990 January-December (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1991 January-December (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 1992 January-1993 December (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 1994 January-September (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 1995 February-1997 December (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 1999 March-December (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 2000 January-May (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 2000 June-December (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 2001 January-February (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 2001 March-December (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Activities/Correspondence, 2002 January-November (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 2003 January-December (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Activities/ Correspondence, 2004 March-2006 June (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Activities/Correspondence, n.d. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Activities/ Correspondence relating to Portsmouth, Virginia, 1987 August-1991 April (Box-folder 3:7)
  - American Participant [AmPart] Program, by the United States Information Agency to articulate US opinion, 1992 January-1993 June (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Arabic Newspapers, n.d. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Articles saved by W. N. Howell's Mother, Josephine ) Edwards Howell, 1930s (Box-folder 4:2)
  - The Assassination of American Diplomats in Beirut, Lebanon- Hearing Publication, 1976 July (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Awards, 1983 March-1992 February (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Biography/ Resume of W. Nathaniel Howell, 1972-1993 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Cards from Time in Kuwait, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Church Bulletins and Memorials, saved by W. N. Howell's Mother, Josephine Edwards Howell, 1930s (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order? Biographies of Speakers, 2001 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order? Budget, 1999 August-2001 May (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order? International Relations Organization [IRO], 2000 September-2001 February (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order? Logistics, 2000 June-2001 July (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?- Media, 2000 June-2001 March (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?- Miscellaneous, 1999 August-2001 April (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?- Notes on Arabic, 2001 February (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?- Program, 1999 June-2001 February (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order? -Security, 2001 February (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?- Sponsors, 1999 September-2001 February (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Dissertation- The Soviet Union and the Kurds- Introduction, Chapters I, II, and III, 1965 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Dissertation- The Soviet Union and the Kurds- Chapters IV and V, 1965 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Dissertation- The Soviet Union and the Kurds- Chapters VI and VII, 1965 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Dissertation- The Soviet Union and the Kurds- Conclusion, Appendix, and Bibliography, 1965 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Financial Disclosure Statements, 1984 May-1991 March (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Gary Larson Cartoon, 1987 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Guest Lists/ Menus from the American Embassy in Kuwait, 1987 November-1990 June (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Humanitarian Operations Center, 2003 June (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Institute of Global Policy Studies: Birdwood Properties, 1997 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - The Kuwait Diplomacy Institute: Final Report, 1998 November (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Kuwait: New Parliament, New Circumstances, New Challenges, 2002 September (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Lecture Tour Notes, 1991, Folder 1 of 4. (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Lecture Tour Notes, 1991, Folder 2 of 4. (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Lecture Tour Notes, 1991, Folder 3 of 4. (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Lecture Tour Notes, 1991, Folder 4 of 4. (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Lecture Tour Notebook, 1991 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Life Magazine, Volume 62, Number 25, 1967 June 23 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Life Magazine, Volume 42, Number 12, 1967 June 26 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Loose Items from Baby Book, Birthday and Christmas) Cards [see Photograph Albums for Baby Book], 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Loose Items from Baby Book, Drawings [see Photograph Albums for Baby Book], 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Loose Items from Baby Book, miscellaneous [see Photograph Albums for Baby Book], 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Loose Items from Baby Book, Report Cards [see Photograph Albums for Baby Book], 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Name Tags and Business Cards, [1970s], n.d. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - New York Times Magazine, 1967 July 2, 1974 March 24 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - News Clippings, miscellaneous, 1967-1983 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Notes on An Identity Card, a cantata/ poem by Salavdor Arnita, 1971 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Origin of the Carter Doctrine- Camp David Accords and the Iran Hostage Crisis, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Patches and Cards worn when Political Advisor at United States Central Command, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - People Weekly, 1991 May 6 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Poems, miscellaneous, saved by W. N. Howell's Mother, Josephine Edwards Howell, 1930s (Box-folder 7:14)
  - Programs from Time in Kuwait, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 7:15)
  - Post-Traumatic Stress Research for Kuwait, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Receipts/ Reimbursements for Events at the American Embassy in Kuwait, 1989 January-1990 July (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Siege of Montana Freedmen, in which Howell served as a FBI consultant, 1995 September-1996 June (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Sugar Bowl, 1990 December (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Thesis Paper by Michael D. Capps: The Gulf Monarchies,1992 January (Box-folder 8:5)
  - US Central Command [USCENTCOM] Invitations, 1986 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Virginia State Parks Maps, saved by W. N. Howell's Mother, Josephine Edwards Howell, 1930s (Box-folder 8:7)
- Series II: Memoranda Books
  - Address Book from Beirut, 1970s (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Address Book, 1990s (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Appointment Book, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Appointment Book while working at US Central Command [USCENTCOM], 1985-1986 (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Appointment Book, 1995 (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Appointment Book, 1996 (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Appointment Book, 1997 (Box-folder 8:14)
  - Appointment Book, 1998 (Box-folder 8:15)
  - Memoranda Book on Lectures, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8:16)
  - Notes on Office of Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon, and Syria Affairs [NEA/ARN] meetings, 1970s (Box-folder 8:17)
- Series III: Photographs and Photograph Albums
  - Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - AE Ambassador Baseball Team- Kuwait, n.d. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Autographed Photographs, 1960s-1980s (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Beirut Civil War, 1976 June (Box-folder 9:4)
  - City of Portsmouth, Virginia- Celebration of Ambassador Howell's Return, 1991 February, Folder 1 of 2. (Box-folder 9:5)
  - City of Portsmouth, Virginia- Celebration of Ambassador Howell's Return, 1991 February, Folder 2 of 2. (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Dinner at Monticello- Night with John Casteen, 1991 April (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Embassy Kuwait- Education Reception, 1988 September (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Fort Bragg- field exercises, 1986 (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Kuwait during Iraqi Invasion, 1991 (Box-folder 9:10)
  - Loose Items from Baby Book, Baby/ School Age Pictures [see Photograph Albums for Baby Book], 1940s- 1950s (Box-folder 9:11)
  - Loose Photographs, miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 9:12)
  - Minister of Defense, Sheikh Nawaf Al-Ahmed Al-Sabah, signing for purchase of F-18 aircraft, 1989 (Box-folder 9:13)
  - Northern Cyprus, 2001 (Box-folder 9:14)
  - Photos taken at the Conference, The Liberation of Kuwait: Dawning of a New World Order?,2001 February (Box-folder 9:15)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1960s- 2000s (Box-folder 9:16)
  - Postcards saved by Howell's Mother, Josephine Edwards Howell, 1930s (Box-folder 9:17)
  - Scottish Rite Temple on Marafie Foundation USA, n. d. (Box-folder 9:18)
  - UN Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees, n.d. (Box-folder 10:1)
  - US Central Command Visits to Pakistan, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - US Navy Visit During Tanber Protection Regime, 1988 March (Box-folder 10:3)
  - USS Deyo DD-989, photograph and map, n.d. (Oversize 10)
  - USIA Lecture Tour- Sicily, Palermo, and Firenze, 1992 (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Photograph Album- W. Nathaniel Howell's Baby Book, 1939- 1950s (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Photograph Album- Howell's Guest book- personal, 1970s-1990 (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Photograph Album- Christmas In Kuwait, 1988 December (Box-folder 10:7)
- Series IV: Restricted Material
  - Birth Certificate- Wilson Nathaniel Howell, 1939 September (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Claims in Connection to Loss of Personal Belongings in Kuwait, 1989 July-1992 October (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Declassified Security File on W. Nathaniel Howell, 1985 February (Box-folder 11:3)
  - Performance Evaluations for W. Nathaniel Howell, 1974 August-1986 May, Folder 1 of 2. (Box-folder 11:4)
  - Performance Evaluations for W. Nathaniel Howell, 1986 May- 1992 June, Folder 2 of 2. (Box-folder 11:5)
  - Reimbursements in Connection to Travel and Personal Damages in Kuwait and while serving as Political Advisors [POLAD], 1985 August- 1992 July (Box-folder 11:6)
  - Travel Vouchers, 1987 June-1994 July (Box-folder 11:7)